Finding Aid for Jack Flechsig papers, 1919-1988.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Jack Flechsig Papers, 1919-1988 1970-1988
Flechsig, Jack
1.3 linear feet (including outsize)
2013107 Aa 2
Jack Flechsig (1922-2011) served as the Art Director for WXYZ-TV Channel 7 in Detroit, Mich. for 39 years. This collection includes station publications, copies of his work (set designs, advertisements, promotional items, etc.), as well as papers of various family members.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Brenna Moloney (Donor no. 10896 ) in February 2013
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Jack Flechsig was born May 30, 1922 in Detroit to Helen and Otto Flechsig. He attended Wayne State University and was a Second Lieutenant in the United States Army Air Forces during WWII and served as a navigator flying in 52 missions. Flechsig was a member of the Directors Guild of America and the Theatre Department at Wayne State University. He was also a lifelong Puppeteer and a member of the Puppeteers of America. On January 15, 1949, he married Constance McBrearty, to whom he was married for 62 years, giving them 8 children and 11 grandchildren. Flechsig spent his professional career as an Emmy Award winning (1980s) Art Director for WXYZ-TV Channel 7, beginning in 1948 when the station first began broadcasting. He retired 39 years later in January of 1988. Flechsig died January 17, 2011 in Bloomfield Twp. at the age of 88.
WXYZ-TV is an ABC affiliated station and the third of ABC's five original owned and operated TV stations (after New York and Chicago). The station was created out of the ABC-owned radio station WXYZ (1270 AM). The station originally began broadcasting in 1948 from studios located in the Maccabees Building in downtown Detroit. In 1959, broadcast facilities moved to Southfield, Mich. The station began broadcasting in color in 1964. By 1978, WXYZ-TV was the second most-dominant TV station in the U.S. in terms of local viewership. It remains a major television station in Detroit.
Jack Flechsig (1922-2011) was the Art Director of WXYZ-TV Channel 7 in Detroit for 39 years. The majority of this collection covers his time working at the station; however, part of the collection contains papers of the families of Flechsig and his wife, Constance. The collection is divided into two series: the Personal series and the Business series.
Subjects:
Flechsig, Jack.; Television stations--Michigan--Detroit.; Television stations--Michigan--Southfield.; WXYZ-TV (Television station: Southfield, Mich.)
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Scenography.
- Personal
  The Personal series (0.3 linear feet, 1919-1972) consists of material of various family members of Jack Flechsig and his wife, Constance McBrearty Flechsig. These family members include Madge Walker (aunt of Constance), Helen Flechsig (mother of Jack), Saidee McBrearty (mother of Constance), Jerome McBrearty (cousin of Constance), and Otto Flechsig (father of Jack). This series is organized with a designated folder for each family member containing their personal items as well as a miscellaneous folder with unassigned materials of interest. The Personal series is varied, with items relating to the American Red Cross (Madge Walker's service award), the Palette and Brush Club (Saidee McBrearty), the American Legion Auxiliary (Helen Flechsig), and the University of Detroit (Jerome McBrearty), among others, located within the personal folders of Flechsig's family.
  - College photograph, undated (Box 1)
  - Helen Flechsig, 1945-1947 (Box 1)
  - Jerome McBrearty, 1935 (Box 1)
  - Madge Walker
    - American Red Cross service award, undated (Box 1)
    - Photographs, undated (Box 1)
    - Scrapbook with loose papers, 1919-1966 (Box 1)
      (scattered)
  - Miscellaneous, 1928-1972 (Box 1)
  - Saidee McBrearty, 1948-1965 (Box 1)
- Business
  The Business series (1 linear foot, 1950-1988) consists of items related to Flechsig's time at WXYZ-TV as the Art Director. This series provides insight into program advertising, television set design, as well as the work environment of WXYZ-TV. Some items of interest include a wide variety of Flechsig's designs, detailed lists of television rates and research as well as programming schedules, and many photographs from on set at the station (one photograph of President Nixon on the WXYZ-TV set is of note).
  - Correspondence-community outreach, 1971 and undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-company cards, undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence-company programs invitations, 1972-1979 (Box 1)
    (with gaps)
  - Design awards, 1980-1985 (Box 1)
  - Designs, 1982 and undated (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1982 and undated (Box 2)
  - Program guides and magazines, 1950-1983 (Box 1)
  - Program posters and promotional items, 1978 and undated (Box 1)
  - Program schedules and calendars, 1974-1983 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1980 and undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1988 and undated (Box 1)
  - Retail newsletter, Winter 1982 (Box 1)
  - Slides from set, undated (Box 1)
  - Sticker and pin designs, 1969 and undated (Box 1)
  - Television ratings and research, 1970-1982 (Box 1)